Guide to the Aleksander Wat Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1942-1982; Series II; 9.59; (24 boxes)
  Series II includes holograph and typescript drafts of Aleksander Wat's major publications, including the volumes of poetry, memoirs and collections of essays. Material also includes original audio recordings and transcripts for Wat's "oral memoir" Mój Wiek, which was edited and published posthumously by Czesław Miłosz and Paulina Wat. In addition to files on his major publications, writings include numerous notebooks, typescript drafts of essays, and loose holograph drafts of poems. Material dated after 1967 is related to the posthumous publication of Wat's work and some of the later material is transcribed by Paulina Wat. Many of the folders include notes by Paulina Wat and others.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 47-49 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Major Works of Poetry and Prose
    Arranged alphabetically by title of work.
    - Ciemne świecidło
      - Drafts, some corrected, holograph and typescript, 1960s, undated (Box 11, Folder 350-358)
      - Related material, including partial drafts, notes, table of contents, clippings, and book cover image, 1958-1960s, undated (Box 11, Folder 359-362)
      - Wiersze śródziemnomorskie, printed versions, annotated by Wat, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 363-364)
      - Wiersze, printed versions, annotated by Wat, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 365-366)
      - Proofs, corrected, 1960s (Box 11, Folder 367-369)
      - Title page, proof, 1968
      - Notes by Andrzej Wat, undated (Box 12, Folder 370)
    - Dziennik bez samogłosek
      Includes material for Moralia and Kartki na wietrze.
      - "Moralia," Zeszyt A, holograph, 1952 or 1953 (Box 12, Folder 371)
      - "Moralia," Zeszyt B, holograph, undated [1950s] (Box 12, Folder 372)
      - "Moralia," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 12, Folder 373)
      - "Moralia," typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 12, Folder 374-375)
      - "Moralia," typescript, corrected (copies), undated (Box 12, Folder 376-377)
      - "Dziennik podróży," holograph, 1955-1956 (Box 12, Folder 378)
      - "Dziennik podróży," typed transcript, undated (Box 12, Folder 379)
      - Draft of "Paszportyzacja" and Dziennik 1963-1964, typescript carbon, corrected, 1970s? (Box 12, Folder 380)
      - "Wierzę -- nie wierzę (1963-1965)," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 13, Folder 381)
      - "Kartki na wietrze (1966-1967)," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 13, Folder 382)
      - "Dziennik bez samogłosek," typescript, corrected, 1970s? (Box 13, Folder 383-386)
      - "Dziennik bez samogłosek," Paulina Wat's copy, typescript, corrected (copy), undated (Box 13, Folder 387-389)
      - "Dziennik bez samogłosek," typescript, corrected (copy), undated (Box 13, Folder 390-391)
      - Drafts, chapters and fragments, typescript (including copies), some corrected (Box 14, Folder 392-398)
    - Mediterranean Poems
      English translation by Czesław Miłosz of Wiersze śródziemnomorskie.
      - Draft, typescript, corrected (copy), circa 1977 (Box 14, Folder 399)
      - Excerpts, typescript carbon, undated (Box 14, Folder 400)
    - Mój Wiek
      - 1, 2, 3, 4, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 47, Item barcode 39002109977968)
        Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - Wat-Milosz 1, 6, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 47, Item barcode 39002109977976)
      - Wat-Milosz 2, 7, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 47, Item barcode 39002109977984)
      - przepisane 3, 8, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 47, Item barcode 39002109977992)
      - przepisane 4, 9, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 47, Item barcode 39002109978008)
      - prezepisane 5, 10, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 47, Item barcode 39002109978016)
      - 11, 12, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 48, Item barcode 39002109978024)
      - 13, 14, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 48, Item barcode 39002109978032)
      - 15, 16, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 48, Item barcode 39002109978040)
      - 17, 18, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 48, Item barcode 39002109978057)
      - 19, S.A: wiersze Alekadia..., 1963-1965; 1 (Box 48, Item barcode 39002109978065)
      - 21, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 48, Item barcode 39002109978073)
      - 23, 24, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 49, Item barcode 39002109978081)
      - 25, 26, 27, Wat Memoirs, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 49, Item barcode 39002109978099)
      - 28, 29, 30, 31, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 49, Item barcode 39002109978107)
      - 32, 33, 34, 35, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 49, Item barcode 39002109978115)
      - 36, 37, 38, 39, 1963-1965; 1 (Box 49, Item barcode 39002109978123)
      - Draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated, circa 1971 (Box 18, Folder 418-422)
      - Draft, typescript carbon, corrected (continued), undated, circa 1971 (Box 19, Folder 423-428)
      - Draft, typescript, corrected by Czesław Miłosz (copy), undated (Box 19, Folder 429-431)
      - Draft, typescript, corrected by Czesław Miłosz (copy) (continued), undated (Box 20, Folder 432-433)
      - Fragments and related material, undated (Box 20, Folder 434-443)
      - Clippings, reviews and other related printed material, 1970s (Box 21, Folder 444-451)
      - List of addresses, undated (Box 21, Folder 452)
      - Notes by Paulina Wat, manuscript, 1970s (Box 21, Folder 453-454)
      - "Powrót," by Paulina Wat, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 21, Folder 455)
    - Ucieczka Lotha
      - Notebooks, undated [1940s] (Box 21, Folder 456-461)
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, undated [1940s] (Box 21, Folder 462)
      - Printed excerpts, with holograph notes, 1949, 1957 (Box 21, Folder 463)
  - Poetry
    - Poems, holograph, undated (Box 22, Folder 464-470)
    - Poems transcribed from notebooks, typescript, some corrected, 1970s (Box 22, Folder 471-482)
    - "Poemat bukoliczny," typescript (and copies), undated (Box 22, Folder 483-486)
    - Two proposals, manuscript, undated (Box 22, Folder 487)
    - Poems from notebook II, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 23, Folder 488-489)
    - "Niedrukowane wiersze Aleksandra Wata," typescript carbon, undated (Box 23, Folder 490-491)
    - Poems from "Brulion ostatni," holograph (copies), undated (Box 23, Folder 492)
    - "Wierzby w Ałma Acie," holograph (copy), undated (Box 23, Folder 493)
    - Poems published in Twórczość, printed version (copy), undated (Box 23, Folder 494)
    - Poems published in Więź, printed version (copy), 1982 (Box 23, Folder 495)
    - Cover of Mediterranean Poems (copy), undated (Box 23, Folder 496)
    - Drafts of poems from notebooks (copies), undated (Box 23, Folder 497-502)
    - "O poezji błahostka," typescript, corrected (copies), undated (Box 23, Folder 503)
    - "Mala Dalila ...," typescript, corrected (copy), undated (Box 23, Folder 504)
    - Poems from "Zeszyt łososiowy," typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 23, Folder 505)
    - Poems from "Zeszyt różowy," typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 23, Folder 506)
    - "Namopanik charuna," typescript carbon, undated (Box 23, Folder 507)
    - Poetry by Maurice Scève, Polish translations, typescript, undated (Box 23, Folder 508)
    - "Na śmierć prezydenta," typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 23, Folder 509)
    - "Ja z jednej strony i ja z drugiej strony mego mopsożelaznego piecyka" (fragments), typescript carbon, undated (Box 23, Folder 510)
  - Essays, Short Fiction and Playscripts
    - Literary essays, drafts, holograph and typescript, some corrected, 1940s-1960s (Box 23, Folder 511-513)
      Folders include lists of their contents.
    - Essay on Krasiński, drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 24, Folder 514-515)
    - Notes for a portrait of Stalin, holograph and typescript, 1962-1963 (Box 24, Folder 516)
    - "Też do jednej hipotezy," typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 24, Folder 517)
    - "Notatki do odczytów," holograph, 1960s (Box 24, Folder 518)
    - "Do semantyki," typescript carbon (fragment), undated (Box 24, Folder 519)
    - "Głos w dyskusji," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 24, Folder 520)
    - "La doctrine et la pratique du communisme ...," typescript (corrected), undated (Box 24, Folder 521)
    - "La refonte de l'âme ...," typescript, undated (Box 24, Folder 522)
    - Fragments of essays, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 24, Folder 523)
    - "Sur la langue et la poésie polonaise," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 24, Folder 524)
    - Fragment on Polish-Russian relations, holograph, undated (Box 24, Folder 525)
    - "Jeszcze trochę polemiki," holograph, undated (Box 24, Folder 526)
    - "Co Rosja straci na wygnaniu chińczyków," typescript, undated (Box 24, Folder 527)
    - "Massacre pour les Juifs," typescript, undated (Box 24, Folder 528)
    - Fragment on Communism, typescript, undated (Box 24, Folder 529)
    - "Komentarze do wojny społecznej," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 24, Folder 530)
    - "Nareszcie początek," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 24, Folder 531-532)
    - "Polska" (fragment), typescript, undated (Box 24, Folder 533)
    - "Amnestia dla wielkich," typescript, undated (Box 24, Folder 534)
    - "Do KPP-owców," typescript, undated (Box 24, Folder 535)
    - "Moje spóźnione postscripta do listu 34," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 24, Folder 536)
    - "Kennedy -- de Gaulle," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 24, Folder 537)
    - "Text o nieokreślonej narazie przynależności," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 24, Folder 538)
    - "Dlaczego Zachód (świat) nie rozumie komunizmu," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 24, Folder 539)
    - Fragment, holograph, undated (Box 24, Folder 540)
    - Review of Gałczyński by Andrzej Stawar, typescript, undated (Box 24, Folder 541)
    - "Na wypadek konfiskaty Wierszy Śródziemnomorskich," typescript, corrected, 1963 (Box 24, Folder 542)
    - "Kobiety z Monte Olivetto," typescript, corrected, undated [1950s] (Box 24, Folder 543)
    - Lecture notes, holograph and typescript, 1960s (Box 25, Folder 544-555)
    - Political essays (fragments), drafts, holograph and typescript, some corrected, undated (Box 25, Folder 556-559)
      Includes notes on Stalin.
    - Essays on Communism (fragments), drafts, typescript, some corrected, 1960s (Box 25, Folder 560-568)
    - Essays on Communism (fragments), drafts, typescript, some corrected (continued), 1960s (Box 26, Folder 569-575)
    - "Suplementa do uczonych," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 26, Folder 576)
    - "Rapsodie polityczne," typescript and holograph, corrected, undated (Box 26, Folder 577-578)
    - "Partia komun. franc.," typescript, undated (Box 26, Folder 579)
    - "Dostojewski i Stalin," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 26, Folder 580)
    - "Chiny," typescript, corrected, 1963 (Box 26, Folder 581-582)
    - "Wstęp do geometrii politycznej," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 26, Folder 583-584)
    - "O polityce," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 26, Folder 585)
    - "Uwagi starego czytelnika gazet," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 26, Folder 586)
    - "Plan Marshala," typescript, undated (Box 26, Folder 587)
    - "Do genealogii komunistycznego praxis," typescript, corrected, 1960s (Box 26, Folder 588)
    - "Dwufazowość polityki sowieckiej komunistycznej ...," typescript, undated (Box 26, Folder 589)
    - "Sytuacja wojska," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 26, Folder 590)
    - "Wlaściwy początek Iwana Denisowicza," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 26, Folder 591)
    - Anthologie de la Poésie Polonaise (edited by Konstanty Jeleński), notes, circa 1965 (Box 26, Folder 592-594)
    - "Coś niecoś o Piecyku," drafts, typescript, corrected, 1967-1981 (Box 26, Folder 595-601)
      Includes a translation into French.
    - "Uwagi o tekscie," typescript, corrected (copy), undated (Box 26, Folder 602)
    - "Trzy starości," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 27, Folder 603)
    - Untitled prose (fragment), typescript carbon, undated (Box 27, Folder 604)
    - "Komentarze do wojny społecznej," typescript, undated (Box 27, Folder 605)
    - "Gucio zaczarowany," typescript, undated (Box 27, Folder 606)
    - "Tuwim," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 27, Folder 607)
    - "Żyd wieczny tułacz," translations into English and French, typescript carbon, undated (Box 27, Folder 608-609)
    - "Prowokator" (notes?), holograph, undated (Box 27, Folder 610)
    - "Niech żyje Europa," typescript carbon, corrected, circa 1960 (Box 27, Folder 611-612)
    - Notes in French, typescript, undated (Box 27, Folder 613)
    - Essay on the translation of poetry, typescript carbon and typescript (copy), 1967 (Box 27, Folder 614-616)
    - "Aleksandra Wata ABC Komunizmu," typescript (copy), undated (Box 27, Folder 617)
    - Short essays, typescript and typescript carbon, undated (Box 27, Folder 618-619)
    - "Quelques apercus sur les rapports entre la litterature et la realite sovietique," typescript (copy), 1962 (Box 27, Folder 620-621)
    - "Quelques apercus sur la poesie traduite," typescript (copy), corrected, 1967 (Box 27, Folder 622)
    - "Le realisme et le reel in Russie," typescript (copy), 1963 (Box 27, Folder 623-624)
    - "Klucz i hak," typescript, printed version (copy) and list of corrections, typescript (copy), 1963, undated (Box 27, Folder 625-626)
    - "La mort d'un vieux bolchévik," printed version, 1963 (Box 28, Folder 627)
    - "Antyzoil albo rekolekcja na zakończenie roku," typescript carbon, undated (Box 28, Folder 628)
    - "Projet d'edition Silva," notes and related material, typescript and typescript carbon, 1959-1961 (Box 28, Folder 629)
    - Unidentified transcript, typescript (corrected), 1966 (Box 28, Folder 630)
    - "Narodziny poety," typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 28, Folder 631)
    - "Writers in exile," typescript, corrected, 1967 (Box 28, Folder 632)
    - "La refonte de l'Âme," typescript and typescript carbon, undated (Box 28, Folder 633)
    - "Historia ostatniej rewolucji w Anglii," typescript carbon, undated (Box 28, Folder 634)
    - "S. P. Stanisław Rogoż," printed versions and typescript, 1942, undated (Box 28, Folder 635)
    - "Co mnie dzieli od katolicyzmu ...," typescript, corrected, 1963 (Box 28, Folder 636)
    - "O ciemnych poetach i ciemnych czytelnikach," typescript, corrected, 1969 (Box 28, Folder 637)
    - "Słowo wstępne do 1-go tomu Rapsodii Politycznych ," typescript and typescript carbon, 1969, undated (Box 28, Folder 638)
    - "Coś o potędze poezji," typescript and typescript carbon, [1963?], 1969 (Box 28, Folder 639)
    - "Ewangelia także jako arcydzieło literatury," typescript (corrected), circa 1969 (Box 28, Folder 640)
    - "Dlaczego piszę wiersze?," typescript, corrected, circa 1969 (Box 28, Folder 641)
    - "Esej o stosunkach pisarza do czytelników i krytyków," typescript, corrected, 1969 (Box 28, Folder 642)
    - "Powieść," typescript and carbon, 1922, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 643)
    - Biographical information about Aleksander Wat, typescript and clippings, undated (Box 28, Folder 644)
  - Memoirs
    - "Notatki osobiste," holograph, 1961-1965, undated (Box 28, Folder 645-655)
    - "Zamarstynów," holograph and typescript, corrected, 1978, undated (Box 28, Folder 656-657)
    - "Do not z dziennika," manuscript and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 28, Folder 658)
    - "Fragmenty wspomnień," holograph and typescript, 1963-1964, undated (Box 28, Folder 659-666)
    - "Fragmenty wspomnień," holograph and typescript, 1963-1964, undated (Box 29, Folder 667-672)
    - "Fragment z notatnika 1961," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 29, Folder 673)
    - "Kartki z notatników," holograph, undated (Box 29, Folder 674-675)
    - "Rękopisy do wspomnień," holograph, undated (Box 29, Folder 676-679)
    - "Mój krótki porachunek," holograph, 1966-1967 (Box 29, Folder 680-684)
    - "Fragmenty do Mojego Wieku" (Kijów), holograph, undated (Box 29, Folder 685)
    - "Fragmenty wspomnień," holograph, undated (Box 29, Folder 686-687)
    - "Fragmenty wspomnień" (Ili), holograph and typescript, undated (Box 29, Folder 688)
    - "Notatki do wspomnień," holograph, undated (Box 29, Folder 689)
    - "Fragment wspomnień" (Lata powojenne), holograph and typescript, undated (Box 29, Folder 690)
    - "Notatki rożne," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 29, Folder 691)
    - "Z pamiętników," holograph and typescript, undated (Box 30, Folder 692)
    - "Omarchadziew," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 30, Folder 693)
    - "Fragmenty tekstu dot. pomocy dla Polaków w Kazachstanie," manuscript [by Paulina Wat?], undated (Box 30, Folder 694)
    - "Moja żona" (1967) typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 30, Folder 695-696)
    - "Brulion ostatni," typescript and typescript carbon, undated (Box 30, Folder 697-698)
    - "Niedokończone opowiadanie po śmierci," typescript, undated (Box 30, Folder 699)
    - "Notatka-wspomnienia" (1963-1967), typescript, 1969 (Box 30, Folder 700-705)
    - "Żaby," typescript carbon, undated (Box 30, Folder 706)
    - "Stosunek do śmierci" (1967), typescript, undated (Box 30, Folder 707)
    - "Dalszy ciąg czegoś, co trzeba znaleźć" (1964) typescript, corrected, undated (Box 30, Folder 708)
    - "Z dziennika prowadzonego w Berkeley z dnia 2.6.64," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 30, Folder 709)
    - "Karteczki z notatnika," typescript, corrected, 1977 (Box 30, Folder 710-711)
  - Notebooks
    Notebooks numbered with arabic numerals (Zeszyt 1, etc.) contain short notes about readings and writings, citations and personal notes. Other notebooks include drafts of writings.
    - "Notatniki I, II," notebooks, 1953 or 1954 (Box 30, Folder 712-715)
    - "Zielony zeszyt" (I and II), notebooks, 1967, undated (Box 30, Folder 716-717)
    - "Zielony zeszyt" (I and II), typescript, corrected, undated (Box 30, Folder 718-719)
    - "Zielony zeszyt" (I and II), typescript, corrected (continued), undated (Box 31, Folder 720-722)
    - Loose pages related to "Zielony zeszyt," holograph and typescript, 1963-1969, undated (Box 31, Folder 723-728)
    - "8 notesów rozmaitych," notebooks and typescript, 1960s (Box 31, Folder 729-737)
      One notebook, "zeszyt łososiowy," is transcribed.
    - "Zeszyt I" (memoirs, notes), notebook and typescript, 1967 May-June, undated (Box 31, Folder 738-739)
    - "Zeszyt II" (poems), notebook, undated (Box 31, Folder 740)
    - "Zeszyt III" (1967) typescript, undated (Box 32, Folder 741)
    - "Zeszyt III A," notebook, 1967 (Box 32, Folder 742)
    - "Zeszyt IV" (memoirs, essay, poems, drafts of letters), notebook and typescript, 1965-1966, undated (Box 32, Folder 743-745)
    - "Zeszyt V" (Berkeley), notebook, [1964-1965] (Box 32, Folder 746)
    - "Zeszyt VI" (Berkeley), notebook and typescript, [1964-1965], undated (Box 32, Folder 747-749)
    - "Zeszyt VII" (notes, essays), notebook and typescript, 1967, undated (Box 32, Folder 750-751)
    - "Zeszyt VIII" (notes, essays), notebook and typescript, 1967, undated (Box 32, Folder 752-753)
    - "Zeszyt IX" (notes, essays), notebook and typescript, 1962-1963, undated (Box 32, Folder 754-755)
    - "Ostatni zeszyt," notebook, 1967 (Box 32, Folder 756)
    - "Cytaty I," notebook, undated (Box 32, Folder 757)
    - "Lektury II," notebook, undated (Box 32, Folder 758)
    - "Lektury III," notebook, undated (Box 32, Folder 759)
    - "IV," notebook, undated (Box 33, Folder 760)
    - "Zeszyt 1," notebook, undated (Box 33, Folder 761)
    - "Zeszyt 2," notebook, undated (Box 33, Folder 762)
    - "Zeszyt 3" (i cytaty), notebook, undated (Box 33, Folder 763)
    - "Zeszyt 4," notebook, undated (Box 33, Folder 764)
    - "Zeszyt 5" (i cytaty), notebook, undated (Box 33, Folder 765)
    - "Zeszyt 6," notebook, undated (Box 33, Folder 766)
    - "Zeszyt 7," notebook, undated (Box 33, Folder 767)
    - "Zeszyt 8," notebook, undated (Box 33, Folder 768)
    - "Zeszyt 9" (Francja), notebook, undated (Box 33, Folder 769)
    - "Zeszyt 11" (La Messa), notebook, 1963 January (Box 33, Folder 770)
      There is no notebook number 10.
    - Pocket notebooks, undated (Box 33, Folder 771-772)
    - Pocket notebooks (continued), undated (Box 34, Folder 773-784)
- Personal Papers and Memorabilia, 1915-1985; Series III; 1.88; (5 boxes)
  Series III is organized by type of material.
  Series III includes personal documents, photographs, calendars and agendas. Personal documents consist chiefly of identification cards and documents related to immigration, including documents from the time of the Wat family's exile in Kazakhstan.
  - Documents (PEN Club), 1934 (Box 35, Folder 785)
  - Documents (various), 1941-1967 (Box 35, Folder 786-789)
  - Documents (including London passport), 1942-1946 (Box 35, Folder 790)
  - Documents (Kazakhstan, including copies), 1942-1945 (Box 35, Folder 791-792)
  - Documents (Legitymacje), 1945-1967 (Box 35, Folder 793)
  - Documents (Poland), 1919-1958 (Box 35, Folder 794)
  - Documents (France), 1963-1967 (Box 35, Folder 795-796)
  - Documents (Zapis testamentowy, Paulina and Andrzej Wat), 1977 (Box 35, Folder 797)
  - Documents related to the round-up of Poles in the USSR, undated (Box 35, Folder 798)
  - Curricula vitae and bibliographical information, undated (Box 35, Folder 799-809)
    Includes texts from Aleksander Wat's memorial service.
  - Photographs, 1929-1967 (Box 35, Folder 810-811)
    Includes photographs of Aleksander Wat, his family, friends and colleagues, and reproductions of poetry manuscripts.
  - Photographs, 1915-1967 (Box 36, Folder 812)
  - Calendars, 1950s-1960s, undated (Box 36, Folder 813-820)
  - Calendars (continued), 1950s-1960s, undated (Box 37, Folder 821-829)
  - Address books, 1960s, undated (Box 38, Folder 830-839)
  - Medical and financial papers, 1954-1967 (Box 38, Folder 840-846)
  - Drawings, 1960s, undated (Box 39, Folder 847-851)
    Includes sketches by Jan Lebenstein, Aleksander Wat, Józef Czapski, and Czesław Miłosz.
  - Ephemera, 1942-1985 (Box 39, Folder 852-856)
    Includes announcements, invitations, and visiting cards.
  - Memorabilia (Aleksander Wat's sleep mask), undated (Box 39, Folder 857)
- Writings of Others, 1921-1988; Series IV; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by author.
  Series IV consists chiefly of articles and reviews about the work of Aleksander Wat, as well as poetry dedicated to Wat.
  - Gross, Jan, "Notre Siecle," typescript (copy), undated (Box 40, Folder 858)
  - Herbert, Zbieniew, Raport z oblężonego Miasta, printed version (1983, copy), undated (Box 40, Folder 859)
  - Herling-Grudzinski, Gustaw, review of Wiersze, printed version (1958, copy), undated (Box 40, Folder 860)
  - Iwaniuk, Wacław, poems dedicated to Paulina Wat, printed version, 1978
  - Jeleński, Konstanty, " Kultura, la Pologne en exil," printed version (copy), 1981 (Box 40, Folder 861)
  - Kołakowski, Leszek, typescript (copy), undated (Box 40, Folder 862)
  - Leociak, Jacek, poems dedicated to Aleksander Wat, typescript carbon, 1986 (Box 40, Folder 863)
  - Lourie, Richard, poem dedicated to Aleksander Wat, typescript, undated (Box 40, Folder 864)
  - Łukasiewicz, Jacek, "O poezji Aleksandra Wata," typescript (copy), undated (Box 40, Folder 865)
  - Miłosz, Czesław, "O wierszach Aleksandra Wata," printed version (1967, copy), undated (Box 40, Folder 866)
  - Miłosz, Czesław, "On Aleksander Wat," proof (copy), 1988 (Box 40, Folder 867)
  - Nowosad, W., Józef Czapski, Maria Czapska, Konstanty Jeleński, "Dyskusja okrągłego stołu pamięci Aleksandra Wata," typescript carbon, 1967 (Box 40, Folder 868)
  - Tomaszewski, Marek, "Aleksander Wat: l'Exil et la Memoire," typescript (copy), 1986 (Box 40, Folder 869)
  - Trznadel, Jacek, "O Aleksandrze Wacie," typescript carbon, undated (Box 40, Folder 870)
  - Trznadel, Jacek, "Złe z dobrem w przeplocie," typescript (copy), 1987 (Box 40, Folder 871)